Carlo Lipizzi

Hoboken, New Jersey, United States



clipizzi@gmail.com



linkedin.com/in/clipizzi

Summary

Data Science professional teaching, researching and consulting on Machine Learning and Natural Language Processing.

Professor and Principal Investigator at the Stevens Institute of Technology, NJ, teaching and researching on Natural Language Processing, Machine Learning, and Data Science.

Managing an Engineering practice developing solutions for decision taking using Data Science, Natural Language Processing and Machine Learning.

Experience



Director - Center for Complex Systems & Enterprises

Stevens Institute of Technology

Jun 2021 - Present

The Center for Complex Systems and Enterprises (CCSE) at Stevens Institute of Technology leverageson best practices in Systems Engineering, Data Science, Machine Learning to address the nature of complex socio-technical systems.



Stevens Institute of Technology

Jan 2016 - Present

Teaching and researching on Data Science, Natural Language Processing and Machine Learning at the School of Systems and Enterprises (SSE).



Director - Systems Analytics & Engineering Management Graduate Programs

Stevens Institute of Technology

Jun 2016 - Present

Principal Investigator

Systems Engineering Research Center (SERC)

Apr 2018 - Present

Managing research projects on C4IRS (Command, Control, Communications, Computers, Intelligence, Surveillance and Reconnaissance) using Data Science, Natural Language Processing and Machine Learning.



LCdataLab

Jan 2010 - Present

LCdataLab operates as an Engineering lab developing solutions for complex intelligence problems using Data Science, Machine Learning and Natural Language Processing.

Adjunct Professor

Stevens Institute of Technology Jun 2014 - Dec 2015

Developed and taught Data Science courses.



co-COO & CTO

Feb 2012 - Nov 2012

Worked at the North American branch - Omniticket Network - as co-COO and CTO, building new services and streamlining operational processes.

Principal

Lipizzi Consulting

Jan 2000 - Dec 2009

Lipizzi Consulting delivered Data driven Service Innovation and Management. I launched startups in the US and in EU in consulting and technology.

I covered most of the Product & Service Innovation chain: from product line analysis, market and target analysis to pricing. Activities include the system architecture design required to implement the innovation strategies.

I also provided startups support and operations - management.



Director, Consulting

Telesoft America

Nov 1996 - Dec 2000

Worked in Telesoft America, 100% owned by Telecom Italia group, as Director for the Group Innovation Consulting unit.

In this capacity, I performed business intelligence on markets/competitors, to feed with new products/solutions the Group's offer pipeline.



Senior Business Consultant

Consiel

Jan 1995 - Oct 1996

I delivered IT-centered market strategies for large European clients in Government, Finance and Telecommunications.

I co-founded and co-managed the company subsidiary in Brazil.



Senior Business Consultant

AlmavivA S.p.A.

Jan 1992 - Dec 1994

Within the Almaviva group - formerly Finsiel - I worked for several companies, including the R&D branch -Tecsiel - in the Artificial Intelligence division.

Worked as Management Consultant on Marketing/Innovation - as a project leader in the Telecommunication industry - and in Brazil and Cyprus defining Group strategies and implementing business/activity plans.



Senior Business Consultant

EY

Jan 1990 - Dec 1991

Dual role as Supervisor for Pre-sales for Central and Southern Italy and as Senior Business Consultant, focusing on IT architectures and systems strategies.



Technical Manager

Softsiel

Jan 1988 - Dec 1989

Softsiel was part of the Finsiel/Almaviva group, then part of Telecom Italia.

Created and directed the "Technology Advisory Innovation Center", for the Finsiel Group leading the development and management of the center with P&L responsibilities.

Education



Stevens Institute of Technology

Doctor of Philosophy (PhD), Systems Engineering 2009 - 2015

Title of my dissertation: Extracting Knowledge from Social Media: Social Messages as Conversations.



IMD Business School Executive MBA, Management 1995 - 1996



Sapienza Università di Roma Master's degree, Mathematics 1976 - 1981

Adjunct professor 1980-'81 - Numerical Analysis

Academic Highlights

The last 3.5 years, I taught 470+ data science students, primarily graduates, with classes having one of the largest number of students at Stevens, receiving one of the top evaluation ratings in my school. I was appointed director for the Center for Complex Systems and Enterprises, publishing an average of 6 papers/year. I manage the Engineering Management and Systems Analytics Graduate programs and the School Corporate Education program.

AI/ML/NLP Recent Project Experience

In recent times - from 2018 - I managed projects in the Data Science/Machine Learning area as PI for a total of \$6M. The largest project was 2.5 years long for the DoD. My team had about 25 members and I wrote all the key algorithms and the related prototypes, then transformed into production code by the team. In a second project for the DoD I reused the algorithms I developed, working on a different knowledge base, provided by the sponsor.

Within Stevens, I'm currently managing 2 more NLP-based projects, one for the DoD, one for a financial company. Both are based on my algorithms.

I'm also working as consultant on 2 projects, one for a financial company - optimizing the information extraction from text - one for a law firm - evaluating the impact of news outlet to a company reputation, using Social Media input.

Coding Experience

Python

All my research projects are based on Python. It is used to develop working prototypes/products. The largest research project I was PI of had about 12K lines of Python code. I personally wrote a good portion of it. I developed and teaching a Python course for 4 years. The course has about 100 students/year and it's the most popular we offer in my school.

SQL

Working experience in SQL.

I developed and taught a Data Engineering course, based on the use of SQL.